American Association of University Women-Washington Branch 059
DCPL Special Collections - MLK Library
American Association of University Women-Washington Branch Records
1889-1970
DCPL Special Collections - MLK Library
American Association of University Women. Washington Branch
059
2 Linear feet
4 Boxes
Biographical / Historical
The American Association of University Women (AAUW) was incorporated in 1881 in Boston, Massachusetts as the Association of Collegiate Alumnae (ACA). The Washington Branch of the Association was organized in 1882 and was the first branch of the Association. In 1920, the National Association opened its headquarters in Washington, D.C. at 1634 I Street NW, where they remained until 1960. The Washington Branch shared this facility with the National Association. In 1921 the ACA merged with the Southern Association of College Women to form the AAUW. In the 1940s, the National Association and the Washington Branch entered into a legal battle over the Branch's refusal to admit African-American members (in particular, Mary Church Terrell). The Washington Branch claimed that the National By-Laws allowed the local branches to dictate membership. At the same time, the National Association was asserting its right to terminate the Washington Branch. A federal court ruled that the Washington Branch indeed had the right to dictate its own membership, but that the National Association had the right to terminate the Washington Branch. With the federal ruling handed down, the National Association terminated the Washington Branch and then re-instituted those Washington members who were in support of the National Association as the official Washington Branch. The Washington Branch continued the mission of the National Branch, which was to "carr[y] out a program of education through study groups, panel discussion,…encourage high standards in education, undertake projects to extend local cultural and educational facilities…[and] offer fellowships to aid gifted women…" The Washington Branch continues to work for women's issues to this day.
Custodial History
The collection was originally filed in the Library Vertical File Collection. Because of the unique nature of the materials and the amount of materials available, it was decided that a collection should be created out of the materials, which were then sorted by subject.
Related Materials
Historical Society of Washington, D.C. American Association of University Women – D.C. Branch Records, 1884-1997. MS 540.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of correspondence, bulletins, yearbooks, clippings, legal documents and photographs that document the Washington Branch of the American Association of University Women. The collection is divided into the following three series: Administrative Files, Bulletins, and Yearbooks.
Associations, institutions, etc; Women; Education, higher; Organizational Records; Yearbooks; Ephemera
- Series 1: Administrative Files
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of correspondence, clippings, photographs, meeting announcements, legal documents, and programs. Topics include: Latin American Fellowship, Desegregation of the Washington Branch, National Conventions, and Membership.
  - AAUW v. AAUW-WB, 1946-1949 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - By-Laws, 1934-1950 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Clippings, 1889-1939 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Clippings, 1940-1960 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Clippings - National Headquarters, 1920-1961 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1939-1956 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Elections, 1938-1949 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - History: 20th Anniversary of National Clubhouse, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Meetings, 1938-1953 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Membership, 1925-1950 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - National Convention, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Outreach Programs, 1932-1969 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Photographs, Undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Publicity, 1950-1970 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Series 2: Bulletins
  This series consists of monthly bulletins from the Washington Branch of the AAUW. Although Bulletins were issued from October to May, an annual chronological arrangement was chosen.
  - Bulletins, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Bulletins, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Bulletins, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Bulletins, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Bulletins (Supplements), 1933 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Bulletins, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Bulletins, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Bulletins, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Bulletins, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Bulletins (Supplements), 1937 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Bulletins, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Bulletins, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Bulletins, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Bulletins (Supplements), 1940 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Bulletins, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Bulletins, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Bulletins, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Bulletins, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Bulletins, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Bulletins, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Bulletins, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Bulletins, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Bulletins, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Series 3: Yearbooks
  This series consists of annual yearbooks published by the Washington Branch of the AAUW. These materials are arranged chronologically.
  - Yearbooks, 1921-1922 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Yearbooks, 1927-1928 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Yearbooks, 1928-1929 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Yearbooks, 1929-1930 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Yearbooks, 1931 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Yearbooks, 1932 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Yearbooks, 1933 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Yearbooks, 1934 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Yearbooks, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Yearbooks, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Yearbooks, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Yearbooks, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Yearbooks, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Yearbooks, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Yearbooks, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Yearbooks, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Yearbooks, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Yearbooks, 1944-1946 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Yearbooks, 1946-1948 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Yearbooks, 1950-1951 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Yearbooks, 1952-1953 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Yearbooks, 1953-1954 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Yearbooks (2 Copies), 1954-1955 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Yearbooks (2 Copies), 1955-1956 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Yearbooks, 1956-1957 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Yearbooks, 1957-1958 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Yearbooks (Supplement), 1958-1959 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Yearbooks (2 Copies), 1959-1960 (Box 4, Folder 28)